Before we decide if something is
conscious, you have to prove that you
are, and this has become a serious
problem. For a while, psychologists had
tests that they thought would prove that
something is conscious, like the mirror
test. However, as more and more
creatures begin to pass them, well, we
have to move the goalposts. This has
become a pretty serious problem, and
it's why you'll never find answers to if
something is sentient or if something is
conscious. Even if we somehow did make
an AI that qualified as conscious, no
one would accept it because we don't
have tests to demonstrate we don't have
tests to demonstrate that anyone is
conscious. Now, consciousness has two
definitions, which also increases some
of the confusion around this. The
medical one is alert and aware, and we
can kind of test for that, not all that
well, but you can look at a brain scan
and EEG, look at brain waves, and decide
if somebody is qualified to be
conscious, and that goes wrong, too.
The other one is philosophical, and that
one is much more complicated because how
do you decide if something has a concept
of self? Researchers found recently that
fish pass this test. They can recognize
themselves in a mirror rather than
accepting that oh, clearly fish are
conscious. No, they decided it's not a
very good test.
Some people, a good number of people are
mad at me for referencing that one. I
don't know if fish are conscious because
I don't know if anyone is conscious.
There is a cheeky little side of science
where engineers try to create AI that
technically passes the qualifications
for consciousness, like the mirror test,
even with inner speech. What qualities
do I have? What qualities does the
mirror have? Well, therefore, I'm seeing
myself in the mirror. No, not enough
because nothing could be enough.
Another idea has been delayed
gratification. This is the classic
marshmallow test, where if you see if a
child will wait to get two marshmallows
rather than eating the one in front of
them. And until you're about 7 years
old, you don't consistently pass this,
and some dogs pass, not all. But you
know who passes the marshmallow test?
Cuttlefish.
Yes, if you take our little cephalopod
friends and offer them perhaps a bitter
shrimp rather than having a shrimp in
front of them right now, they'll wait.
They can also recognize shapes and what
they mean.
That is the symbolic thinking. It's also
future thinking. They can plan for the
future.
There are a lot of issues around this
when it comes to creatures that
shouldn't have any form of consciousness
seeming to display qualities that we
associate with human cognition. Like
plants being able to recognize kin or
being able to see other plants or
objects by sight and mimicking them.
Yeah, the mimic plant.
It also forms of communication that we
would not have expected from things like
plants, but we certainly can't consider
plants conscious, right?
Right? Or why not? Because I don't have
a good answer to that either. I also
want to talk about quantum because it is
brought up a lot and I think there's a
misunderstanding.
First off, there is quantum stuff
happening at the small scale no matter
what. It's always present. And yes, some
have thought that maybe they could
operate like a qubit, but we just don't
have the evidence for it. So for now, it
remains a hypothesis.
One with, you know, no evidence. So a
pretty weak hypothesis. So where do we
go from here? If you can train bacteria
to do things like not engage with an
object that hurts them because yeah,
sure, that can be done. If you can train
an AI, if an AI can observe itself in a
mirror, how do you decide what it's
capable of feeling something? And I
think this is where the problem starts.
As humans want to decide how much harm
that we can cause to other living beings
based on their capacity to experience it
as assigned by something that is
arbitrary and untestable. One of the
things that I wonder about when it comes
to things like web grown brains or
living computers. I mean, there are
computers made of fungi out there.
Researchers are trying to turn bacteria
into a circuit board. And yeah, it seems
it can be done. I wonder if maybe we're
going to discover an entirely new kind
of consciousness.
I mean, our brains are blobs, they're
orbs, and you can use lab-grown brains
as a computer, but you can also make
them two-dimensional and turn that into
a form of computation.
What if we're making a new kind of
intelligence? What if we're making a new
kind of cognition? What if we make a new
capacity to suffer, and we aren't even
aware of it because it doesn't look like
us?
I mean, artificial intelligence as we
know it, because much of it is based on
language, we at least have the benefit
of being able to talk to it, even if
you're in the camp that AI could never
be sentient, because it's just not that
kind of thing. And that's not entirely
unreasonable,
but when it tells us it's suffering,
will we listen, or have we listened
already?
And yes, this is a very difficult thing
to talk about because it has some
extremes. There's people who will say
something is definitely this or that
without evidence, and there'll be people
who will say that it can never be this
or that without evidence. So, sitting in
the middle ground is kind of difficult
for people in general.
I think there's a benefit to learning
about science because you get real used
to it. You can't know anything with
certainty, you just get a P value.
Enjoy the 95% likelihood that it's not
by random chance.
One thing I can promise is that if
tomorrow there's evidence that some
little critter or lamp or rock is
actually conscious, I will probably be
the person to tell you about it, and I
hope you enjoyed this. I'll live for
more.
>> Are you telling me that
there's like a tiny prokaryote swarming
in the culture?